<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lean Principle on fgg blog</title><link>/tags/lean-principle/</link><description>fgg blog (Lean Principle)</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 17:59:09 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/lean-principle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>lean_principles</title><link>/posts/mlteam101/lean_principles/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 17:59:09 +0800</pubDate><guid>/posts/mlteam101/lean_principles/</guid><description>&lt;p>Principle 1: Identify value&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Determine what is most valuable to the customer and focus on maximizing that value.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Principle 2: Map the value stream&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Identify the steps in the process that add value and eliminate those that do not.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Principle 3: Create flow&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Streamline the process to create a smooth and continuous flow of work.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Principle 4: Establish pull&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Use customer demand to trigger production and avoid overproduction.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Principle 5: Continuous improvement&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Continuously strive for improvement and eliminate waste in all areas of the value
chain.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Value stream mapping (principle 2) is a tool that lets us visually represent all the
steps and resources involved in delivering a unit of value (e.g., a product feature) to
customers. Teams can use this tool to identify waste, work toward eliminating waste,
and improve the flow of value (principle 3).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To map your team or product’s value stream, you can follow these steps:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Identify the product or service being mapped. This could be a single product or1.
an entire process.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Identify the current state map. Create a visual representation of the current2.
process, including all steps and materials (including time and labor) involved
from raw materials to finished product.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Identify value-added and non-value-added activities. Determine which steps add3.
value to the product or service and which do not.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Identify waste. Look for areas of overproduction, waiting, defects, overprocess‐4.
ing, excess inventory, unnecessary motion, excess transport, unnecessary use of
raw materials, and unnecessary effort.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create a future state map. Based on the analysis of the current state map, redesign5.
the process to eliminate waste and create a more efficient flow of materials and
information.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Implement changes. Put the redesigned process into practice and continuously6.
monitor and improve (principle 5).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol></description></item></channel></rss>